大家好
Alright, hi, everybody.
我是来自 Brain Robotics 团队的 Alex
I'm Alex, from the Brain Robotics team,
在本演示中  我将谈论我们如何在一些
and in this presentation, I'll be talking about how we use simulation
现实世界中的机器人学习问题中使用模拟和域适应
and domain adaptation in some of our real-world robot learning problems.
所以  首先让我开始介绍机器人学习
So, first let me start by introducing robot learning.
机器人学习的目标是使用机器学习
The goal of robot learning is to use machine learning
来学习在一般环境中能运作的机器人技能
to learn robotic skills
that work in general environments.
到目前为止  我们看到的是
What we've seen so far is that
如果你常常控制你的环境
if you control your environment a lot,
你可以让机器人做出很厉害的事情
you can get robots to do pretty impressive things,
而技术开始崩溃的地方
and where techniques start to break down
是当你尝试将这些相同的技术应用
is when you try to apply these same techniques
到更一般的环境时
to more general environments.
他们的思想是  如果你使用机器学习
And the thinking is that if you use machine learning,
那么你可以从你的环境中学习
then you can learn from your environment,
这可以帮助你解决这些泛化问题
and this can help you address these generalization issues.
所以  作为朝这个方向迈出的一步
So, as a step in this direction,
我们一直在关注机器人抓取的问题
we've been looking at the problem of robotic grasping.
这是我们一直在与X的一些人合作的一个项目
This is a project that we've been working on
in collaboration with some people at X.
为了解释我们的问题设置
And to explain our problem setup a bit,
我们将有一个真正的机器人手臂
we're going to have a real robot arm
它正在学习从垃圾箱中拾取物体
which is learning to pick up objects out of a bin.
将会有一台摄像机俯视
There is going to be a camera looking down
手臂的肩膀进入垃圾箱
over the shoulder of the arm into the bin,
从这张 RGB 图像中  我们将训练一个神经网络
and from this RGB image we're going to train a neural network
以了解它应该发送给机器人的命令
to learn what commands it should send to the robot
以成功拾取物体
to successfully pick up objects.
现在  我们想尽量使用尽可能少的假设来解决这个任务
Now, we want to try to solve this task using as few assumptions as possible.
所以  重要的是  我们不会提供
So, importantly, we're not going to give any information
关于我们想要拾取什么类型的物体的任何信息
about the geometry of what kinds of objects we are trying to pick up,
我们也不会提供
and we're also not going to give
有关场景深度的任何信息
any information about the depth of the scene.
所以为了解决这个任务
So in order to solve the task,
模型需要学习手眼协调
the model needs to learn hand-eye coordination
或者需要知道它在摄像机图像中的位置
or it needs to see where it is within the camera image,
然后找出它在场景中的位置
and then figure out where in the scene it is,
然后结合这两者来弄清楚它应该如何移动
and then combine these two to figure out how it should move around.
现在  为了训练这个模型  我们将需要大量的数据
Now, in order to train this model, we're going to need a lot of data
因为它是一个相当大规模的图像模型
because it's a pretty large scale image model.
而我们当时的解决方案是使用更多的机器人
And our solution at the time for this was to simply use more robots.
所以这就是我们所说的  手臂农场
So this is what we call the "Arm Farm."
有六台机器人并行采集数据
These are six robots collecting data in parallel.
如果你有六个机器人  你可以更快地收集数据
And if you have six robots, you can collect data a lot faster
如果跟只有一个机器人相比
than if you only have one robot.
因此  使用这些机器人  我们能够在数千个机器人小时内收集超过一百万次抓握的尝试
So using these robots, we were able to collect
over a million attempted grasps,
因此  使用这些机器人  我们能够在数千个机器人小时内收集超过一百万次抓握的尝试
over a total of thousands of robot hours,
然后使用这些数据  我们能够
and then using this data we were able
成功地训练模型学习如何拾取物体
to successfully train models to learn how to pick up objects.
这是可行  但仍需要很长时间
Now, this works, but it still took a lot of time
才能收集此数据集
to collect this dataset.
因此  这一点激励我们寻找方法
So this motivated looking into ways
减少学习这些行为所需的实际数据量
to reduce the amount of real-world data needed
to learn these behaviors.
一种做法是模拟
One approach for doing this is simulation.
因此  在左侧视频中
So in the left video here,
你可以看到在我们的真实世界设置中进入我们模型的图像
you can see the images that are going into our model
in our real world setup,
而在右侧  你可以看到
and on the right here you can see
我们模拟该设置的重新创建
our simulated recreation of that setup.
现在  将事物转化为模拟的优势在于
Now, the advantage of moving things into simulation
模拟机器人更容易扩展
is that simulated robots are a lot easier to scale.
我们已经能够旋转数以千计的模拟机器人
We've been able to spin up thousands of simulated robots
它们会抓住各种物体
grasping various objects,
使用这种设置  我们能够在短短八个多小时内收集数百万的抓握
and using this setup we were able to collect millions of grasps
in just over eight hours,
而不是原始数据集所需的几周
instead of the weeks that were required for our original dataset.
这对于获取大量数据非常有用
Now, this is good for getting a lot of data,
但不幸的是  模拟培训的模型
but unfortunately models trained in simulation
往往不会转移到真实世界的机器人
tend not to transfer to the actual real world robot.
两者之间存在很多系统性差异
There are a lot of systematic differences between the two.
其中一件大事是不同事物的视觉外观
One big one is the visual appearances of different things.
而另一个重要的就是我们现实世界的物理学和我们的模拟物理学之间的物理差异
And another big one is just physical differences
between our real-world physics
而另一个重要的就是我们现实世界的物理学和我们的模拟物理学之间的物理差异
and our simulated physics.
所以我们所做的就是  我们能够快速
So what we did was, we were able to very quickly
训练我们的模拟模型  以获得大约90％的抓握成功
train our model on simulation to get to around 90% grasp success.
然后  我们部署到真正的机器人上
We then deployed to the real robot,
它的成功率超过20％
and it succeeds just over 20% of the time,
这是一个非常大的性能下降
which is a very big performance drop.
所以为了获得好的表现
So in order to actually get good performance,
我们的做法需要更聪明一些
we need to do something a bit more clever.
所以这个动机考虑了模拟 - 到-现实的转换
So this motivated looking into Sim-to-Real transfer,
这是一组转换学习技术
which is a set of transfer-learning techniques
用于尝试使用模拟数据
for trying to use simulated data
来提高你的实际样本效率
to improve your real-world sample efficiency.
有几种不同的方法可以做到这一点
Now, there are a few different ways you can do this.
这样做的一种方法是在
One approach for doing this is
你的模拟器中增加更多的随机化
adding more randomization into your simulator.
你可以通过更改应用于不同物体的纹理
You can do this by changing around the textures
that you apply to different objects,
改变其颜色
changing around their colors,
改变灯光与场景的交互方式
changing how lighting is interacting with your scene,
以及改变所要尝试捡起的物体的几何形状来实现这一点
and you can also play around with changing the geometry of what kinds of objects
you're trying to pick up.
另一种方法是领域适应
Another way of doing this is domain adaptation,
这是一组学习技术
which is a set of techniques for learning
这适用于当你有一些共同的结构的两个数据领域
when you have two domains of data that have some common structure,
但仍然有些不同
but are still somewhat different.
在我们的情况下  这两个领域将是我们的模拟机器人数据
In our case the two domains are going to be our simulated robot data
和我们的真实机器人数据
and our real robot data.
还有一些功能级别的方法可以做到这一点
And there are feature-level ways of doing this
并且也有像素级别的方法可以做到这一点
and there are pixel-level ways of doing this.
现在  在这项工作中  我们尝试了所有这些方法
Now, in this work, we tried all of these approaches,
并且在本演示中  我将首先关注
and in this presentation, I'm going to focus primarily
领域适应这方面
on the domain adaptation side of things.
因此  在特征级别领域培训中
So, in feature-level domain adaptation
我们要做的是我们将采用我们的模拟数据
what we're going to do is we're going to take our simulated data,
拿出我们的真实数据
take our real data,
在两个数据集上训练相同的模型
train the same model on both datasets,
然后在网络的中间特征层
but then at an intermediate feature layer of the network,
我们将附上相似性损失
we're going to attach a similarity loss.
而相似性损失将会促使特征的分布
And the similarity loss is going to encourage the distribution of features
在整个领域变得相同
to be the same across both domains.
一种很好的方法
Now, one approach for doing this which has worked well recently
被称之为领域 - 对抗神经网络
is called Domain-Adversarial Neural Networks.
它的运作的方式是将相似性损失
And the way these work is that the similarity loss is implemented
作为一个小型的神经网络来实现  它试图根据它所接收到的输入特征来预测领域
as a small neural net that tries to predict the domain
based on the input features it's receiving,
然后其余的模型试图尽可能地
and then the rest of the model is trying
混淆这个领域分类器
to confuse this domain classifier as much as possible.
像素级别的方法尝试从不同的角度解决问题
Now, pixel-level methods try to work at the problem
from a different point of view.
我们尝试让像素级别的图像看起来更逼真  而不是试图学习领域不变特征
Instead of trying to learn domain invariant features,
we're going to try to transform our images at the pixel level
我们尝试让像素级别的图像看起来更逼真  而不是试图学习领域不变特征
to look more realistic.
所以我们在这里的做法是我们采取一个生成对抗网络;
So what we do here is we take a generative-adversarial network;
我们从模拟器中提供一张图像
we feed it an image from our simulator,
然后输出看起来更逼真的图像
and then it's going to output an image that looks more realistic.
然后我们将使用这个生成器的输出
And then we're going to use the output of this generator
来训练我们想要训练的任何任务模型
to train whatever task model that we want to train.
现在我们要同时训练
Now we're going to train both
发电机和任务模型
the generator and the task model at the same time.
我们发现在实践中  这很有用
We found that in practice, this was useful
因为它有助于将发电机输出信号
because it helps ground the generator output
用于实际训练下游任务
to be useful for actually training your downstream task.
好的  退一步说
Alright. So taking a step back,
功能级别的方法可以在你有不完全相同的相关领域的数据时学习域不变特征
feature-level methods can learn domain-invariant features
when you have data from related domains
功能级别的方法可以在你有不完全相同的相关领域的数据时学习域不变特征
that aren't quite identical.
同时  像素级方法可以将数据
Meanwhile, pixel-level methods can transform your data
转换为更接近真实世界的数据
to look more like your real-world data,
但实际上它们的运作不是完美的
but in practice they don't work perfectly,
并且发生器输出中仍然存在一些小的瑕疵和不准确性
and there are still some small artifacts
and inaccuracies from the generator output.
所以我们的想法是    为什么我们不把这两种方法结合起来
So our thinking went, "Why don't we simply combine both of these approaches?"
我们可以应用像素级别的方法
We can apply a pixel-level method
尽可能多地转换数据
to try to transform the data as much as possible,
但这不会让我们一路畅通无阻
and this isn't going to get us all the way there,
但是随后可以在此基础上附加一个功能级别的方法
but then we can attach a feature-level method on top of this
以尝试进一步缩小现实的差距
to try to close the reality gap even further,
并将这些形式组合在一起  形成我们所说的抓取 gen
and combined these form what we call the grasp gen
它是像素级和特征级域适应的组合
which is a combination of both
pixel-level and feature-level domain adaptation.
在这视频的左半部分
In the left half of the video here
你可以看到一个模拟的抓握
you can see a simulated grasp.
在右半边你可以看到我们的发电机的输出
In the right half you can see the output of our generator.
你可以看到它正在学习一些非常酷的东西
And you can see that it's learning some pretty cool things
从绘制托盘应该看起来的样子
in terms of drawing what the tray should look like,
在手臂上绘制更逼真的纹理
drawing more realistic textures on the arm,
绘制物体正在投射的阴影
drawing shadows that the objects are casting.
它还学会了当手臂在场景中移动时  如何在手臂上绘制阴影
It's also learned how to even draw shadows
as the arm is moving around in the scene.
它当然不是完美的
And it certainly isn't perfect.
在周围仍然有些奇怪的颜色斑点
There are still these little odd splotches of color around,
但它肯定是在学习一些有关如何让图像看起来更真实的东西
but it's definitely learning something
about what it means for an image to look more realistic.
这对于获得大量漂亮的图像是很好的
Now, this is good for getting a lot of pretty images,
但是对于我们的问题而言  重要的是这些图像是否真的有用于
but what matters for our problem is whether these images are actually useful
将它们减少到所需的实际数据
for reducing them onto real-world data required.
我们发现它的确可以
And we find that it does.
因此  稍微解释一下这个图表：
So, to explain this chart a bit:
在x轴上是所使用的实际样本的数量
On the x-axis is the number of real-world samples used,
并且我们比较了不同方法的性能
and we compared the performance of different methods
在我们将它们改变为给模型提供的实际数据的同时我们这么做了
as we vary them onto real-world data given to the model.
当我们只使用模拟数据时  蓝条是我们的表现
The blue bar is our performance when we use only simulated data.
红色条是我们使用真实数据时的表现
The red bar is our performance when we use only real data,
橙色条是我们使用模拟和真实数据
and the orange bar is our performance when we use both simulated and real data
以及我一直在谈论的领域适应方法时的表现
and the domain adaptation methods that I've been talking about.
我们发现当我们仅使用原始真实世界数据集的2％时
And what we found is that when we use just 2%
of our original real-world dataset,
并且我们将领域适应应用于它
and we apply domain adaptation to it,
我们能够获得相同的性能水平
we're able to get the same level of performance
因此这减少了真实世界所需的样本数量
so this reduces the number of real-world samples we needed
减少了50次
by up to 50 times, which is really exciting
这对于不需要大量时间运作机器人来学习这些抓握行为而言非常令人兴奋
in terms of not needing to run robots for a large amount of time
to learn these grasping behaviors.
此外  我们发现  即使我们将
Additionally, we found that even when we give
所有真实世界的数据都提供给模型
all of the real-world data to the model,
当我们也提供模拟数据时
when we give simulated data as well,
我们仍然能够看到性能的进步
we're still able to see improved performance
这意味着我们在这个抓握问题上尚未达到数据容量限制
so that implies that we haven't hit the data capacity limits
for this grasping problem.
最后  有一种方法可以在没有真实世界标签的情况下训练此设置
And finally, there's a way to train this setup
without having real-world labels,
当我们在此环境中训练模型时
and when we trained the model in this setting,
我们发现我们仍然能够在现实世界的机器人上获得相当不错的性能
we found that we were still able to get pretty good performance
on the real-world robot.
现在  这是 X 和 Brain 大型团队的工作成果
Now, this was the work of a large team
across both Brain as well as X.
我要感谢与我合作的所有人
I'd like to thank all of my collaborators.
这是原始文件的链接
Here's a link to the original paper.
如果人们有兴趣了解更多的细节  可以看看所提供的一篇博文
And I believe there is also a blog post,
if people are interested in hearing more details.
谢谢
Thanks.